David Shaner
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
David Shaner papers
1937-2007, bulk 1968-1998
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Shaner, David
2.8 linear feet
The papers of ceramicist David Shaner measure 2.8 linear feet and date from 1937-2007, with the bulk of the material from 1968-1998. Shaner's career as a ceramicist in Big Fork, Montana, is documented through scattered correspondence, subject files, studio working files, writings and notes by Shaner and others, exhibition catalogs and other printed material, and photographs.
Provenance
The David Shaner papers were donated in 2010 by Ann Shaner, David Shaner's widow.
Related Material
Also found at the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with David Shaner, conducted by Gerald Williams on June 17, 2001.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
David Shaner (1934-2002) was a ceramist in Bigfork, Montana.
Shaner was born in Pottstown, Pennsylvania in 1934. He attended Kutztown State Teachers College and in 1957 entered the Master of Fine Arts program at Alfred University. After earning his MFA, he taught ceramics at the University of Illinois, Champaign-Urbana. In 1962 he and his wife Ann permanently relocated to Montana. Shaner served as director of the Archie Bray Foundation in Helena, Montana from 1964-1970. He remained a prolific potter and respected teacher throughout his life. Shaner was diagnosed with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis in 1995 and died in 2002.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of ceramicist David Shaner measure 2.8 linear feet and date from 1937-2007, with the bulk of the material from 1968-1998. Shaner's career as a ceramicist in Big Fork, Montana, is documented through scattered correspondence, subject files, studio working files, writings and notes by Shaner and others, exhibition catalogs and other printed material, and photographs.
Scattered correspondence includes letters, cards, and postcards. Correspondence is primarily with friends and colleagues, but also includes a few letters from galleries and art organizations. Subject files document Shaner's activities as a professional ceramicist. The majority of the files are for art galleries, but also found are files are for studio equipment, supply companies, and professional organizations. Files may include correspondence, agreements, invoices, price lists, receipts, and press releases.
Shaner's studio working files consist of glaze formulas, his kiln log notebook, plans, and kiln documentation. Also found are his studio notes, lists, formulas, manuals and guides for various ceramic processes and tools. A series of writings and notes consist of notes by Shaner, including notes for his artist's statement, as well as draft manuscripts, lectures, and essays by others on the topic of ceramics.
Printed material includes articles documenting David Shaner's career, exhibition announcements and catalogs for exhibits of Shaner's work, and various publications about ceramics. A small number of photographs found within this collection depict kilns and kiln building events, unidentified artists and studio spaces, and artwork. Included is one photograph of David Shaner.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 6 series:
Series 1: Correspondence, circa 1978-1999 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 2: Subject Files, 1961-1998 (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 3: Studio Working Files, circa 1951-1990s (Boxes 1-2; 8 folders)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, 1954-circa 1993 (Box 2; 6 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1937-2007 (Boxes 2-4; 1.4 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, 1968-1990s (Box 4; 4 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Art galleries, Commercial; Artists' studios--Photographs; Ceramicists--Montana; Ceramics.--Equipment and supplies; Glazes--Formulae; Pottery--Technique
Types of Materials:
Drafts (documents); Essays; Lectures; Manuscripts; Notebooks; Notes; Photographs
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Correspondence, circa 1978-1999, Series 1:; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  This series contains a small amount of David Shaner's correspondence, including letters, cards, and postcards. Correspondence is primarily with friends and colleagues, but also includes a few letters from galleries and art organizations. Researchers should note that additional correspondence can be found within Series 2: Subject Files.
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Subject Files, 1961-1998, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
  This series contains subject files maintained by David Shaner to document his activities as a professional ceramicist. The majority of the files are for art galleries where Shaner showed his work. Other files are for studio supplies and equipment, such as burners, cartons, and freight, and supply companies, as well as professional organizations such as NCECA (National Council on Education for the Ceramic Arts). Files may include correspondence, loan forms and other agreements, invoices, price lists, receipts, press releases, order forms, and miscellaneous documentation.
  Subject Files are arranged alphabetically.
  - Anagama, circa 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anne Reed Gallery, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Artifacts [Gallery], 1986-1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Artworks Gallery, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Burners, 1965-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Canecraft-Treenery, 1988-1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cartons (Packaging), 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Clay Place, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Coleman Clay Studio and Gallery, circa 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Contemporary Crafts Gallery, 1979-1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Corks, 1969-1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - E. J. Bartells Co., 1970-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ferrin Gallery, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Flowers, circa 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Foote Mineral Company, 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Foster/White Gallery, 1991-1998 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Frame Design & Sunbird Gallery, 1991-1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Freight, circa 1970-1985 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Gallery Eight, 1989-1997 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Garth Clark Gallery, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Helen Drutt Gallery, circa 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hibberd McGrath Gallery, 1988-1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Holter Museum of Art, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Images Friedman Gallery, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - International Minerals and Chemical Corp., 1964-1973 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Joanne Rapp Gallery: The Hand and the Spirit, 1990-1998 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Kentucky-Tennessee Clay Co., 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Lawrence Gallery, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Mariposa Gallery, 1984-1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Martha Schneider Gallery, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Maveety Gallery, 1990-1997 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Miller Gallery, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - National Lead Company, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - NCECA, 1961-1997 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Northwest Craft Center and Gallery, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Pewabic Pottery, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Pfizer, Inc., circa 1964-1975 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Pot Sales, 1987, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Potter's Wheel Gallery, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - S. Paul Ward, Inc., 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Salem Art Association, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Supplies, 1969-1990 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Sutton West Gallery, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Sylvia Ullman American Crafts, 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Wetsman Collection, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Whitefish Gallery, 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Studio Working Files, circa 1951-1990s, Series 3:; (Boxes 1-2; 8 folders)
  This series contains reference materials, plans, and notes which David Shaner used in his ceramics studio. Included are glaze formulas, Shaner's kiln log notebook, kiln plans drafted by Shaner and others, and guides to kiln construction and use. Also found are many manuals and guides for using tools, clay, firing, and other related topics. This series also includes Shaner's own handwritten notes, lists, and formulas for his work.
  - Glaze Information, circa 1969-1970s, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
  - Kiln Log, 1972-circa 1991 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Kiln Documentation, circa 1978-1991 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Kiln Plans, 1968-1980 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Manuals and Reference Guides, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Manuals and Reference Guides, circa 1951-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Lists, and Reference Materials, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Writings and Notes, 1954-circa 1993, Series 4:; (Box 2; 6 folders)
  This series contains writings and notes by David Shaner and others. Included are two folders of notes by Shaner including notes for his artist's statement, thoughts on ceramics, and inspirational quotations by others, which he wrote down on scraps of paper. Also found are draft manuscripts by Ken Hendry and Jim Robertson, as well as typescripts of essays and lectures on ceramics written by various authors.
  - Notes, circa 1970s-1990s, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Ken Hendry, "Pottery and the Pursuit of Meaning," circa 1980s, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Jim Robertson, "Body Building for Potters," 1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Various Authors, Writings and Lectures about Ceramics, 1954-circa 1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Printed Material, 1937-2007, Series 5:; (Boxes 2-4; 1.4 linear feet)
  This series contains printed material such as articles from magazines, journals, and news papers documenting David Shaner's career, as well as exhibition announcements and catalogs for exhibits of Shaner's work and the work of other ceramicists. Also found are books, magazines, reports, and journals about ceramics, workshop brochures, and various supply order forms. A file of articles on various subjects and a file of reference images were compiled by Shaner.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by type of publication.
  - Articles about David Shaner, 1960-2005 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Articles about Various Subjects, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Book, Clay/Glass: A Guide to Clay and Glass Artists of Northern California, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Book, Papers by Speakers at the Gippsland National Woodfire Conference, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Book, Syllabus for Advanced Ceramics, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1973-2007, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1960-1993, (9 folders) (Box 2, Folder 17-25)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1994-2005, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Journal, The Studio Potter, 1999, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Magazines, 1937, 1957, 1972-1983, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 5-8)
  - Magazines, 1987, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - NCECA Publications, 1988-2006, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
  - Published Essays by Soetsu Yanagi, 1952, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Reference Images, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Reports, Montana Bureau of Mines and Geology, 1958, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Sales Brochure and Order Forms, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Workshop Brochures, circa 1989-1995 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1949-circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Photographs, 1968-1990s, Series 6:; (Box 4; 4 folders)
  This series contains a small number of photographs and slides of an unidentified studio, kilns, and details of kiln construction. Also found are photographs identified as being from Anagama kiln firing events, depicting the kiln construction, and including one photograph of David Shaner. Miscellaneous photographs depict artwork and an unidentified person working in a studio.
  - Photographs of Studio and Kilns, 1968, circa 1970s (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Anagama Events, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Slides, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)